Today's דף daf is י"ד. Yud Daled. We continue with all discussions
about ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah and what it has to physically one
has to look like and other related issues. I just wanted to
do very quick points though relating to yesterday in the middle of
the whole discussion about גוד או אגוד gudo o agud and whether
you can force a division. The גמרא Gemara quoted a classic debate
of בית הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel u'Beit Shammai about
whether a slave that's half free and half slave, whether you force
the master to free him because of the מצוה mitzvah of פרו
ורבו. Pru U'rvu. So I just wanted to take literally two minutes
just to point out one or two important תוספות Tosafos in that
on י"ג עמוד א'. Yud Gimmel Amud Aleph. For example, the first
תוספות, Tosafos, ריש שפחה יכול, reish shifcha yachol, תוספות Tosafos says, אף
על גב דאמר בבעיא יבמות, af al gav d'amar b'vaya Yevamot, דכולי
עלמא מודו בעבד שאין לו חיות, de-kolei alma modu b'eved she-ein lo
chayus, חיות בלא קיום פרו ורבו, chayus belo kiyum Pru U'rvu, that
a slave is not מקיים mekayem פרו ורבו. Pru U'rvu. So if
he's not מקיים mekayem פרו ורבו, Pru U'rvu, what's this whole idea
of saying that you free him for the sake of פרו ורבו?
Pru U'rvu? Okay. והכא נמי ניצת שפחה לא קאי. ve-hacha nami nitza
shifcha lo kayei. And not only that, you could say, well, the
half that's free can still be מקיים mekayem פרו ורבו, Pru U'rvu,
but תוספות Tosafos says okay, but if the whole slave were, if
the person was a full slave, he wouldn't be מקיים mekayem פרו
ורבו, Pru U'rvu, right, because he's a slave. So why does פרו
ורבו Pru U'rvu compel us now to do something about that part
of him that's a slave? והכא נמי ניצת שפחה לא קאי, ve-hacha
nami nitza shifcha lo kayei, כיון שעבד מיוחס אחריה. kevan she'avad meyuchas
achareiha. Okay. And then, and then תוספות Tosafos says, I'm going to
skip the next line about שבת. Shabbos. Anyway, the תוספות Tosafos says,
אומר ר"י, omer Ri, מכל מקום אומר ר"י, mikol makom omer Ri,
לא כופין לרב לעשות בן חורין משום פרו ורבו lo kofin l'rav
la'asot ben chorin mishum Pru U'rvu אם היה יכול לקיים אפילו שבת
כל דהו, im haya yachol l'kayem afilu shevet kol dehu, כיון שאנוס.
kevan she-annus. So again, I'm not going to discuss the details, but
he basically says, well, maybe פרו ורבו Pru U'rvu doesn't apply to
a slave because technically the child is not related to him, you
know, legally, but nevertheless there's an aspect of, you know, the verse
לא תהו בראה לשבת יצרה. lo tohu bera'ah, lashevet yetzarah. There's an
aspect of that verse that is fulfilled. Okay. And that raises an
interesting question about, is the quoted verse לא תהו בראה לשבת יצרה
lo tohu bera'ah, lashevet yetzarah just an explication of the weight of
פרו ורבו Pru U'rvu or is there some other aspect to it?
Right exactly. So תוספות Tosafos says fine, technically it's not פרו ורבו
Pru U'rvu but you still brought offspring into the world. The other
one, תוספות, Tosafos, sort of is a continuation. שנאמר לא תהו בראה.
shene'emar lo tohu bera'ah. תוספות Tosafos says, הדר למיזיל קרא דפרו ורבו.
hadar l'maisi kra d'Pru U'rvu. Just say you're freeing him for the
sake of פרו ורבו. Pru U'rvu. So אומר ר"י, omer Ri, the
same ר"י Ri says, and the מרדכי, Mordechai, okay, not the same
ר"י, Ri, the ריב"ם Rivam says, משום דלשבת יצרה שייך אפילו בצד
עבדות, mishum d'lashevet yeshara shayach afilu b'tzad avdus, which is basically the
same answer. Okay. Anyway, תוספות Tosafos goes on then to say that
if it were just because of פרו ורבו, Pru U'rvu, you wouldn't
have freed him because that's okay, it's one מצוה, mitzvah, but it's
because it's a weighty מצוה mitzvah of this idea of the whole
purpose the world was created, לשבת יצרה, lashevet yetzarah, that creates the
purpose for חז"ל Chazal to make this תקנה takkana to free him.
Okay. So that's like again an interesting exploration of this idea of
לשבת. lashevet. That on the one hand it's not limited to the
parameters of פרו ורבו. Pru U'rvu. A slave whose children are not
considered legally related to him still has an element of לשבת lashevet
because he's bringing children into the world. And but because of the
weight of לשבת lashevet and informing the weight of the מצוה mitzvah
of פרו ורבו, Pru U'rvu, the way the second תוספות Tosafos reads
it, that leads to this special תקנה takkana to free him. Okay.
And then the next תוספות Tosafos gets onto an interesting question
of כופין את רבו, kofin et rabbo, you force the master to
free him. ואם תאמר, ve-im tomar, אמאי כופין, amay kofin, ליתי עשה
דפרו ורבו, laisi assei d'Pru U'rvu, ודחי לא תעשה דלא יהיה קדש.
ve-dichi lo ta'asseh d'lo yihiyeh kadesh. So the reason this slave
can't marry a freed woman is because he's considered to be, it's
a transgression of לא יהיה קדש, lo yihiyeh kadesh, which normally is
a male prostitute, but here it applies to a slave. That's why
he can't marry a freed woman. So תוספות Tosafos says, I don't
understand, marry a free woman, have children, be מקיים mekayem פרו ורבו,
Pru U'rvu, and the עשה, assei, the מצות עשה mitzvot assei of
פרו ורבו Pru U'rvu override the לא תעשה lo ta'asseh of לא
יהיה קדש. lo yihiyeh kadesh. So can anybody understand, guess what an
answer to that would be?
There's also an עשה? assei?
No, that would be a way to go.
But why would you want to do that? If you can just
like
it's sort of no but why did we have to make the
תקנה takkana which is by freeing him? Okay so that's maybe what
you might, Michael. First of all, there's, it's not a necessary, you
only do it when it's necessary to contradict, and here there's a
way to solve it, so that doesn't allow you to override. But
תוספות Tosafos says two other answers. He gets around to that. The
first תוספות Tosafos answer is דאמר רבנו יצחק חדא דמשעת ביאה איכא
לאו, de'amar rabbeinu Yitzchak chada d'misha d'biya ikar lav, לא מקיים עשה.
lo mekayem assei. דמשעת העראה קעבר לאו, de-mishat ha'araah ka'avir lav, עשה
דפרו ורבו לא מקיים עד גמר ביאה. assei d'Pru U'rvu lo m'kayem
ad gmar biyah. So תוספות Tosafos says, as soon as the act
of intercourse begins, you transgress the לאו. lav. The מצוה mitzvah of
פרו ורבו Pru U'rvu you only מקיים mekayem when the act of
intercourse, you know, is complete, when it's possible to lead to ejaculation
and therefore possible to lead to conception. So תוספות Tosafos actually says
it's at stages in the act of intercourse. Of course you could
have said that the act of intercourse is only a הכשר מצוה
hechsher mitzvah for the פרו ורבו. Pru U'rvu. You're not you know.
It's not the act of פרו ורבו pru u'revu itself. Raises interesting
questions. What is the act, right? 'Cause the act, you know, especially
if you say it's the man's מצוה, mitzvah, then the act isn't
giving birth to the children, you know, is the act having the
children, is it? And that becomes very fascinating questions of how do
you define what is the מעשה מצוה maaseh mitzvah of פרו ורבו?
pru u'revu? And then the second answer תוספות Tosfos said is, when
I'm disappointed at everybody here who did not say this, והא דתהא
אשתו ליתני להו לגבי דידה ליכא עשה, v'ha de'tehei ishto lei natni
lehu legabei didah leika assay, the,
because she, maybe you didn't want to say that she didn't have
a מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, pru u'revu, but if you know
the classic rabbinic approach is that although there's a debate in the
גמרא, Gemara, that the woman doesn't have the מצוה mitzvah of פרו
ורבו. pru u'revu. So could be עשה דוחה לא תעשה assay docheh
lo saaseh for him? He can be allowed to transgress, but who's
allowing her to transgress? She's not doing any מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, and
then the rest of this תוספות Tosfos gets into a whole big
discussion about under what circumstances is it forbidden to free slaves, and
do we allow the freeing of slaves in order to fulfill מצוות,
mitzvos, and we would allow you to transgress, you the master are
going to transgress the prohibition of freeing slaves in order to allow
the slave to do a מצוה. mitzvah. So do we allow some
one person to transgress to allow another person to fulfill a מצוה?
mitzvah? Okay, so a lot of really interesting questions about that. Anyway,
that was just about yesterday, but that's a lot of good stuff
I didn't want to pass over. Okay, yes?
I thought that like a ממזר mamzer specifically ends up marrying a
שפחה. shifcha. Right. So he's free. Yes. And he can marry a
שפחה. shifcha. Right. Yet this person who if he was an עבד
eved he could marry a שפחה, shifcha, now that he's a half-עבד
eved and half-בן חורין... ben chorin...
so תוספות, Tosfos, yeah.
I'm sorry, what are you asking?
An עבד eved can marry a שפחה, shifcha, right? And you can
also set it up, right, you can make, why can't you make
the free half an עבד כנעני? eved Kena'ani?
Yeah, so תוספות Tosfos gets at that exact question, why don't we
allow, why isn't there a way to do this with some case
of a ממזר mamzer or whatever. So that's the other, the second
half of תוספות. Tosfos. Yeah, so all those good questions are discussed.
Okay, let's get back to the גמרא Gemara where we left off.
So we pick up on the top of יד עמוד א. yud
daled amud aleph. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ורמינהי, U'reminhu, okay. So we had basically said that if you are,
now we're talking about the physical, shift gears a bit, we're talking
about the physical scroll of a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah,
and it's actually not limited to the ritual ספר תורה, Sefer Torah,
it's a scroll used you know as a book for
learning, and could have the תורה נביאים וכתובים Torah Nevi'im u'Kesuvim all
in the same scroll. But the גמרא Gemara said the one sort
of thing you have to do is make sure that at the
beginning there's a blank piece of parchment in order to get it
around, you know, to begin the wrapping and at the end there's
another blank piece of parchment. And the way תוספות Tosfos explains the
גמרא, Gemara, which really makes sense, is like if you think about
the way people roll up their מגילת אסתר, Megillas Esther, we're not
talking that there are two bars, which really is the only way
that really makes sense to do a big scroll 'cause then you
can close the book in the middle as it were and open
it up in the middle. If you have to go all the
way to the beginning, you know, it's going to take forever to
get to your right place. Some people said, well, maybe you leave
the other side scrolled so you can stay it, but then why
not make another bar? Especially if you have a huge scroll. So
I really don't understand. Need a bar? No, a pole, a pole
to roll it on, to roll it on, an עץ eitz to
roll it on. So you know, if you're going to have a
huge scroll that has all of תנ״ך, Tanach, I cannot understand how
functionally you want to be doing this without having two poles to
roll it on. But whatever reason it is, there's only one pole.
And anyway, so the way תוספות Tosfos understands, רש״י Rashi understands you
roll from the beginning to the end, which makes no sense 'cause
then you're opening it up backwards. So תוספות Tosfos says no, you
roll from the end to the beginning. And if you're rolling from
the end to the beginning, the piece of קלף klaf you leave
at the end is enough of a blank קלף klaf to get
the first way around the bar, the pole, because you know, you
don't want to put the words directly against the pole. And the
last piece of קלף klaf at בראשית Bereishis after is enough to
go all the way around to essentially be a blank piece of
קלף klaf that wraps the whole thing. Okay?
He switches, רש״י Rashi switches,
כי תניא עושה בראשו כדי לגול היקף ובסופו כדי לגול עמוד. ki
sanya oseh b'rosho k'dei l'gol heikef u'v'sofo k'dei l'gol amud.
He just switches the גירסא. girsa. All right, anyway. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, top of יד עמוד א.
yud daled amud aleph. ורמינהי, U'reminhu, it's the last in this. תחילת
הספר וסופו כדי לגול. techilas ha'sefer v'sofo k'dei l'gol. So the beginning
and the end is enough to wrap. So מאי כדי לגול מאי?
mai k'dei l'gol mai?
So in order to wrap what? To wrap the pole or to
wrap all the way around? אי כדי לגול עמוד קשיא היקף. ei
k'dei l'gol amud kashya heikef. This one way or another this contradicts
what you just said. If the beginning and the end is enough
to just go around a pole, right,
that's wrapped around, so then it contradicts what you said that one
end has to be enough to go around the entire circumference.
ואי כדי לגול היקף, v'ei k'dei l'gol heikef, and if they're both
big enough to go around...
Okay,
each one goes around the appropriate thing. It's going around, one of
them is going around the pole and the other is going around
the entire circumference. רב אשי אמר כי תניא ההיא בספר תורה. Rav
Ashi amar ki tanya hahi b'sefer Torah. No, no, no, that's talking
about a ספר תורה Sefer Torah because a ספר תורה Sefer Torah
actually does have two poles. Okay, דתניא d'tanya like we learned in
a בריתא, braitah, כל הספרים נגללים מתחילתן לסופן, kol hasfarim niglalim mitichilatan
l'sofam, all of them are wrapped from the beginning to the end,
which sounds like רש"י, Rashi,
but I think תוספות Tosafot has a different גרסה girsa or something,
לתחילתן l'tchilatan or something. Okay, again, it's just hard to imagine, I
mean, yes, the גרסה girsa printed in our גמרא Gemara supports רש"י,
Rashi, but it's just hard to imagine what you're doing rolling up
a book so that you open it from the end. Okay, וספר
תורה נגלל לאמצעיתו. v'sefer Torah niglal l'emtzi'ito. But anyway, however you roll
a normal one, either from the end to the beginning or beginning
to the end, a ספר תורה Sefer Torah has two poles, and
because it has two poles you can keep it closed in the
middle. Right? Now, of course, that makes sense but not just for
a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, it makes sense for anything that's large.
So if you're talking about your assumption is that נביאים וכתובים Nevi'im
u'Ksuvim are all coming as individual works and every ספר sefer in
נביאים Nevi'im is separate, okay, then you understand. I mean, although still
a book like ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, but okay, even so, you know, you
understand that you don't need two poles. ספר תורה Sefer Torah is
big, you need two. So presumably, would it be but that was
presumably this would also include if you put all of נביאים Nevi'im
together, certainly if you put all the תנ"ך Tanakh together. Okay, so
anyway, but okay, we're not talking about these really as ritual objects.
Yes, one of them one minute,
okay, I guess let's just finish this. ועושה לו עמודים אילך ואילך,
v'oseh lo amudim ilach v'ilach, you make a pole on both sides.
אמר רבי אלעזר בר רבי צדוק, Amar Rabi Elazar bar Rabi Tzadok,
כך היו כותבי ספרים שבירושלים עושים ספריהם. kach hayu kotvim sefarim sheb'Yerushalayim
osim sifreihem. That's what the people, the scribes in Jerusalem used to
do. And again, the simple פשט pshat of this גמרא Gemara is
that we're not talking about these as ritual objects, which is then
why you wonder, so if we're not talking about them as ritual
objects, sort of like somebody asked the other day, why not let
the market decide? Like why not let people figure out what makes
the most sense? But maybe it's sort of saying that it's like
it's not כבוד kavod to a ספר תורה Sefer Torah to have
it, even if you for some stupid reason want to just have
one pole and constantly be rolling, you know, maybe they demand it
by a ספר תורה Sefer Torah because it's, you know, it's כבוד
kavod to not always be doing that. But it is an interesting
question, like what are the rabbis' job here if they're not talking
about these as ritual objects? And it really must be just to
ensure that some parameters maintain the proper respect for these. Or for
example, what we said yesterday, you don't have all of נביאים Nevi'im
together, at least according to some opinions, or all of תנ"ך Tanakh
together, because then you're not, certainly you don't have all whatever according
to some opinions תנ"ך Tanakh together, because then you're not maintaining clear
lines of distinction between the different ספרים. sefarim. So that would be
the role of the rabbis, but not in terms of ritual objects.
Mikah, you had your hand up before?
I was just like visually things in the הלכות halachot did they
find anything that shows us that the תורה Torah and נביאים Nevi'im
were all...
Oh, yeah, I don't know about whether they found... I mean, those
poles would have disintegrated anyway.
But just that they're in the same scroll, the תורה Torah and...
Oh, yeah, that's an interesting question, yeah, I don't know, I don't
know. I mean, I don't know how much we we retained intact.
ישעיהו Yeshayahu was the biggest ספר sefer that they had intact. Right.
How do we know that these are not used as ritual objects?
Did I miss something that says in...
I mean, רש"י Rashi said it all along, but you know,
there's... What? Yeah, רש"י Rashi in the beginning said
where did רש"י Rashi say? I think so.
I thought רש"י Rashi said it somewhere earlier. But anyway, but because
what would you be using all of these for? Like some of
these ספרים sefarim are never read as הפטורה, Haftarah, they're never whatever.
I mean, there's not a context here for them.
All I know is 100 years ago I was taking שיעור shiur
with Rabbi Soloveitchik, and he was talking about קריאת שמע, Kriat Shema,
and whether you're proofreading or whether you're reading like you're... Right. I
remember clearly he said the way that the ancient חכמים chachamim used
to say קריאת שמע, Kriat Shema, they would take a ספר, sefer,
they would take a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, open it up, and
read קריאת שמע Kriat Shema from it.
Okay, I don't know if that's true, but even if that's true,
that proves my point, because that's not a ritual object. That's a
book, that's a ספר. sefer. It's a ritual object the same way
my ש"ס Shas is a ritual object.
But on the contrary, it's why I daven.
No, fine, the same way my סידור siddur is a ritual object.
The same way my ש"ס Shas is a ritual object. It's not
a ritual object like in order to be יוצא yotze קריאת התורה
Kriat haTorah your ספר תורה Sefer Torah has to look this way.
It's the way to give you access to the text. So it's,
yes, it's a holy text, but ultimately it's a way to give
you it's like any book on any ספר sefer on your bookshelf
is a ritual object. It's not ritual in the
sense I don't really see
Would you say that you are not יוצא yotze קריאת שמע Kriat
Shema if you read it from a ספר תורה Sefer Torah that
did not satisfy these criteria? No. Which means that these are not
ritual requirements, okay. You're using it as a source, as a place
where the text is written. We can discuss it more later, but
I think there's a big difference. Okay, yes.
All right, so
at the beginning you stated you can't separate. Right. But it says
that you need to have enough to wrap the pole. Right.
But you only
have enough for four lines.
Michael asked that the other day. So, well, first of all, if
you're actually doing it for the ספרים sefarim that you can make
the cut at the line, it actually says you have to make,
get it at the top so that you can separate it and
it could be beginning at the top. So what you would do
is then you'd sew on another piece of parchment. Right, if you
cut it at the line, you know, to separate out the books
of נביאים, Nevi'im, you had a one big
compilation, then you would have to sew on a piece of parchment
at both ends to allow you now to roll it. I see.
So there's always—you can always add. But if you basically have, but
if the top of the קלף klaf starts with four lines because
the bottom one here at the end of one, then after you
cut it, it's not starting at the top. But if you cut
it you can always add a blank קלף. klaf. Yeah, Michael.
So according to this not being used as ritual objects, you don't
have to have all the other הלכות halachos like סתם STaM and
all that, right? Right.
Well, this is why we're not discussing those other הלכות. halachos. Right,
right, right, right. Yeah, exactly.
This is—so these are basically...
Just like writing it in script and whatever, just...
Yeah, I mean, that's an interesting question, when they would write ספרי
תורה Sifrei Torah as, you know, סתם ספרים, stam sefarim, would they
insist that it be written in כתב אשורית? Ksav Ashuris?
I don't know. You know, it gets to that whole question about
כל הספרים נכתבים בכל לשון. kol hasefarim nichtavim bechol lashon. Every time
you
see—it's really important—every time you see discussions of ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah,
we immediately assume that the requirements are for ספר תורה Sefer Torah
for us to use for קריאת התורה, Krias HaTorah, okay? But you
have to really realize that the standard use of these ספרים sefarim
were as like books on their bookshelves, you know? So therefore, now
you could go the other way. The רמב"ם Rambam says the whole
list of גמרא Gemara that has a whole requirements for ספרי תורה,
Sifrei Torah, which clearly are about ritual objects, are not just about
using it as a ספר, sefer, right? The רמב"ם Rambam says that
all of those things are not required for קריאת התורה Krias HaTorah
in שול. shul. Oh, for קריאת התורה Krias HaTorah in שול, shul,
he says you can basically use a חומש. Chumash. All of those
are to be יוצא yotze the מצווה mitzvah of כתיבת ספר תורה.
ksivas Sefer Torah. So sometimes you could take like all the—you know,
we assume standard ritual—there are like three categories: מצוות כתיבת ספר תורה,
mitzvas ksivas Sefer Torah, ספר תורה Sefer Torah for reading in שול,
shul, and just a book on my bookshelf, right? So we assume
that the sort of high ritual requirements are in the middle category,
but one of רמב"ם's Rambam's readings is no no, that's only for
מצוות כתיבת ספר תורה. mitzvas ksivas Sefer Torah. You can pretty much,
you know, wide range. So this question about like what language could
it be written in, you know, that standard כל הספרים בכל לשון
kol hasefarim bechol lashon חוץ מספר תורה chutz miSefer Torah whatever, you
know, which script it could be written in, that's a good question
whether
we're—what aspect of ספר תורה Sefer Torah we're talking about. Yeah.
These ספרים sefarim that we have today are from קומראן, Qumran, and
I know it may not be...
That's what מיכל Michal was asking about. Yeah. I don't, yeah...
They were heretics so would it matter?
Not exactly heretics, but whatever. Anyway, that's what מיכל Michal was asking
about. All right, let's go on. All right, they were—they were a
different sect. Okay, moving on. All right, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
Okay, and they would have said you were a heretic. All right,
so the גמרא Gemara goes like this. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
אין עושים ספר תורה לא ארכו... Ein osin Sefer Torah lo orko...
speaking about where was this—what is this being said about? Because this
seems like a very strange type of a requirement. Let's take a
look.
אין עושים ספר תורה לא ארכו יותר על הקיפו ולא הקיפו יותר
על ארכו. Ein osin Sefer Torah lo orko yoseir al hekefo velo
hekefo yoseir al orko. So basically you've got...
okay, here's your scroll, okay? This is the ארכו, orko, okay? And
we're going to say that the ideal here is ששה טפחים, shisha
t'fachim, which is like what is it, like 18 inches or so?
So
that's like a small ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Okay, what?
This is much more than 18.
This is—this is more than 18 inches?
Yes.
One foot and a half.
Really? A book—a piece of paper is—give me a piece of paper.
That's 12 inches, right?
and a half. 18 is... here. Okay, there.
Okay, that's about—so that's roughly the size. Okay, so anyway, so that
high and the circumference around has to also be 18 inches. Once
fully written and all scrolled up. Okay, so and again assuming חז"ל
Chazal assume that pi is 3. Does everybody know that circumference equals
2 pi r, which is basically pi times—why is that funny? Pi
times diameter, so if pi is 3, so that means that the
diameter—what?
Some of us decided to go to rabbinical school because this wasn't
our stage.
Okay, anyway,
so—so it's pi times diameter, which is three times the diameter, and
if the circumference is also ששה טפחים, shisha t'fachim, okay, it's going
to say the circumference is the same, then that means the diameter
is שני טפחים, shnei t'fachim, okay? Which means that a טפח tefach
is about an inch and a half, the diameter is 3 inches.
All right, six inches. Okay, so
two טפחים tefachim. *tefachim* which is about 18, which is about 18
inches, and two טפחים tefachim. *tefachim* which is about six inches. Okay.
So this is what your ספר תורה sefer torah *sefer Torah* has
to look like. Is that about six inches? Let's see if it's
drawn to scale. If this is about...
I know, so I'm approximating it at 12 for... whoops, it's a
lot thinner. Okay.
That's basically, that's to scale, okay. That's what your ספר תורה sefer
torah *sefer Torah* has to look like. All right. Let's take a
look. Yes.
No, you would write the small, the thickness of the קלף klaf,
*klaf* and the size of the script would have to be done
in a way, this is the size of the קלף klaf *klaf*
you begin this way. You begin with a קלף *klaf* that's six...
that's six טפחים tefachim, *tefachim* tall, and you have to get a
קלף *klaf* that's either thin enough, in a script that is tight
enough, or you could say big enough and thick enough, but it's
but actually, so that the circumference is going to also be six
טפחים tefachim, *tefachim*, which means like that the width is going to
be two טפחים tefachim, *tefachim*. Okay.
We have evidence of many ancient scribes who threw themselves off the
top of... All right.
Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says, now we'll
see later this six טפחים tefachim. *tefachim* just so you know where
this number is coming from, the מהרש''א *Maharsha* points out, and I
believe he's right, that later we're going to say that the לוחות
luchos *Luchot* were six טפחים tefachim *tefachim* tall. So that's probably where
this six טפחים tefachim. *tefachim* is coming from. Okay. So אין עושין
ספר תורה sefer torah לא ארכו יתר על היקיפו ולא היקיפו יתר
על ארכו *ein osin Sefer Torah lo orko yoter al hekefo velo
hekefo yoter al orko*, length not greater than the circumference, nor circumference
greater than the length, so it's not just you limit it in
one direction. It has to be equal. The circumference can't be greater
than the length. Now, I did it six and six because the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say that, but here it's not
saying it has to be six, it's just saying it has to
equal the length. So but it has to be this proportion. Okay.
So שאלו את רבי
*sha'alu et Rabbi*, so they asked Rabbi, ספר תורה sefer torah בכמה
*sefer Torah bekama*? How... so what is it? אמר להן *amar lahen*,
so here it gets to the word גויל *gevill*, בלוחות ששה *beluchot
shisha*. If it's גויל *gevill*, it's six. Now, גויל *gevill* is when
you use the entire thickness of the skin, of the leather. Okay,
here's another little interesting point, which
is... yes, yes, yes. Here is your animal, moo. Okay, now anyway,
okay. Here's... yes, thank you. Okay, this is and this is the
skin on its back, this is where its hair grows. So, if
you go ahead and use the entire thickness of the skin, that's
called גויל *gevill*. What גויל *gevill*? גויל *gevill* is the entire thickness
of the
skin, full grain leather. The other thing they would do is, okay,
cut it in half
and use the... no, the actual... the point of the cut, okay,
because apparently that would be the place where it would be the
smoothest in order to do the writing. So they would use the
point of the cut. If you would use the point of the
cut for the outer part, that would be called קלף *klaf*. If
you would use... but you would always be writing on the point
of the cut. Okay, if you did גויל *gevill* you would write
here, you would write on... but if you... if you did these
other things, and this is called דוכסוסטוס *duchsustus* or whatever, דוכסוסטוס *duchsustus*.
Okay, anyway, okay. So, that's... so you can either write a ספר
תורה sefer torah *sefer Torah* on גויל *gevill*, on full grain leather,
and then you would write it where the hair was, or you
could cut... cut it and do half the thickness and write it
where the point of the cut was and that would be called
קלף *klaf*. All right. Yes, yes. Is it...
is it the top or the... is it still... can you use
a dead animal or a kosher dead animal? Or do you have
to שחט *shacht* it in order to use
a ספר תורה sefer torah *sefer Torah*? No, you don't have to
שחט *shacht* it. It has to be from a kosher species.
Right, but you can use it once it's naturally dead? Yes, yes.
Okay. So it says like this...
there's some discussion around... מגילה Megillah *Megillah*, whatever, I sort of get...
yeah, I have to check exactly. Okay. So it says like this.
Okay, fine. So the ברייתא *Beraita* says like this. So בקלף *beklaf*...
so
it says, okay, בקלף איני יודע *beklaf eini yodea*. So... I'm sorry,
בקלף בכמה איני יודע *beklaf bekama eini yodea*. So how... what would
be the right height for a קלף *klaf*? Like, I don't know.
But again, the point is like I'm not really getting it because
it's all proportional. So if it was a thicker... if the קלף
*klaf* was thinner,
right, if it's thinner, if you still have to keep the height
the same as the width, I don't understand what he's saying because
so if you have a thinner... if you have a thinner parchment,
if you have a roll of thinner parchment, so you have... and
you have... so you would just have to write... no, you have
to write bigger. Bigger. Bigger. But I don't understand why the שיעור
shiur *shiur* would be different. Why would the שיעור shiur *shiur* be
different? Keep the שיעור *shiur* the same and write bigger. I don't
understand, anyway, whatever. Bigger. Bigger. Bigger. But I don't understand what the
question is that the שיעור would be different. Why would the שיעור
be different? Keep the שיעור the same and write bigger. I don't
anyway whatever. All right. So רב הונא כתב Rav Huna katav now
רב הונא כתב שבעין ספרי דאורייתא Rav Huna katav shivin sifrei d'Oraisa
רב הונא Rav Huna wrote seventy ספרי תורה sifrei Torah ולא אירמי
ליה אלא חד velo istrami lei ela chad and only one was
he able to get the height the same as the circumference and
maybe also being
six טפחים. tefachim Okay. רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov
כתב חד katav chad אמשכא דעגלי amshka d'eglei on the skin of
a calf ואירמי ליה ve'istrami lei and it worked out. So maybe
that skin was the exact right, like you know, sort of a
thickness to allow this to be done. יהבו ביה רבנן עינייהו, yavu
bei rabanan einaihu, so of course he got so lucky because other
people seventy times they couldn't get it, he got it on his
first try. So they all gave him the evil eye ונח נפשיה
venach nafshei and he died. So there you go.
So either you'll never get it or you'll get it and you'll
die in the making. I don't know what to tell you. I
don't know what to say. I don't know what to say. אמרו
ליה רבנן לרב המנונא amru lei rabanan le'Rav Hamnuna the rabbis said
to רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna כתב רבי אמי ארבע מאה ספרי תורה
katav Rabbi Ami arba meiah sifrei Torah since we mentioned that this
rabbi did seventy, they
said רבי אמי Rabbi Ami wrote 400 ספרי תורה. sifrei Torah. So
he said אמר להו amar lehu he said to them דילמא תורה
צוה לנו משה כתב. dilma Torah tziva lanu Moshe katav. All right,
I can't believe that. That's not literal. Maybe what it meant is
he wrote 400 times תורה צוה לנו משה. Torah tziva lanu Moshe.
So תוספות Tosafot points out דילמא תורה צוה לנו משה dilma Torah
tziva lanu Moshe ואמר רבי יצחק ve'amar Rabbi Yitzchak דאותו פסוק קרי
תורה de'oso pasuk karei Torah כדאמר פרק ג' דסוכה kedamar perek gimmel
de'Sukkah קטן היודע לדבר katan hayodea ledaber אביו מלמדו תורה aviv melamdo
Torah
the father teaches תורה Torah to the son as soon as he
can start
speaking. What's תורה? Torah? מאי תורה? mai Torah? תורה צוה לנו משה.
Torah tziva lanu Moshe. Okay, that's the distillation of the idea of
תורה. Torah. All right. So אמר ליה רבא לרב זירא amar lei
Rava le'Rav Zeira so now we're going to have similar types of
reports that are going to be reinterpreted so that they're not just
crazy exaggerations. אמר ליה רבא לרב זירא amar lei Rava le'Rav Zeira
נטע רבי ינאי ארבע מאה כרמי nata Rabbi Yannai arba meiah karmei
רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai planted 400, you know, vines. Now again, the
most logical thing to say would be the number was an exaggeration,
right? The most logical thing to say would be the number would
be an exaggeration, right, rather than to say the definition of the
noun meant something else, but he's redefining the noun. אמר ליה amar
lei דילמא שתים כנגד שתים ואחת יוצא זנב. dilma shtayim keneged shtayim
ve'achas yotzei zanav. Maybe it doesn't mean like a whole huge vineyard.
Maybe it means, you know, two vines in parallel and one coming
like out between them, because that's considered to be a vineyard for
the הלכה halacha of like who plants a vineyard can go back
from war even as small as those five vines. So maybe it's
a very minimum version of that. Okay, fine.
Now מיתיבי mitivei back to our question about the proportions.
ארון שעשה משה aron she'asah Moshe אמתיים וחצי ארכו ואמה וחצי רחבו
ואמה וחצי קומתו. amatayim vachatzi orko ve'amah vachatzi rochbo ve'amah vachatzi komaso.
Okay, so the ארון aron that משה Moshe made, this is a
פסוק pasuk from the פסוקים psukim was two and a half אמות
amos long, an אמה amah and a half wide, and an אמה
amah and a half tall. באמה בת ששה טפחים be'amah bas shisha
tefachim and we're going to assume like we normally do the אמה
amah is six טפחים. tefachim Okay, now so what does that mean?
So that means
okay,
so two and a half, two and a half times six is
fifteen. Whoops. Okay, fifteen טפחים, tefachim one and a half, so it's
nine טפחים, tefachim okay, and
nine.
Okay. These are all just all in טפחים, tefachim? okay, that's the
ארון. aron. All
right. Fine. These are all measured in טפחים. Tefachim Okay,
now באמה בת ששה טפחים.
be'amah bas
shisha tefachim. Now והלוחות ארכן ששה ורחבן ששה ועובין שלשה.
vehaluchos arkan shisha verochban shisha ve'ovyan shelosha. Now this is where we're
probably getting the idea of six
from this, from—what happened to my black marker? That was the best
marker. Okay.
You got one in here too?
Okay.
I'm sorry. This is six טפחים Tefachim? by six טפחים. Okay, now
the לוחות luchos were basically they were—they're not those nice לוחות luchos
like that look like that. Okay, sorry, sorry. According to the גמרא,
Gemorah. they're basically rectangular solids. Okay. These are the לוחות luchos and
they were made of sapphire.
Okay, so the לוחות luchos are what? The לוחות luchos are what?
ששה
טפחים בששה טפחים
shisha tefachim be'shisha
tefachim and square
by ועובין
שלשה.
ve'ovyan
shelosha.
Okay, and three. ששה טפחים בששה טפחים shisha tefachim be'shisha tefachim ועובין
שלשה. ve'ovyan shelosha. Okay, and three. ומונחות umunachos and they were placed
מונחות
כנגד ארכו של ארון. munachos keneged orko shel aron. Okay, so and
they were placed length-wise. So basically you've got these here, which are
what? Well, six by six. Okay, so you've got these
like that.
Well, I'm not sure how to show this.
Okay, anyway, six and six. Okay,
so we're going to have by twelve, we're going to have three
left here. Okay. So
we'll put them both next to each other. They're put next to
each other, okay, they're three high and they're going six deep.
Did that well?
I did that well, once I got started right. Okay, so anyway,
okay, so, and how much you have left on the back? You
have three left on the back. Three left on the back and
three left on the side. Everybody see that? Right? We can take
out. We can do the—we can remove the three-deep part.
The important point rather than just to say also is that the
לוחות luchos did not look like the McDonald's sign.
I just said that before. You were too busy talking.
Okay,
so basically
you've got three here and three here, okay? Because this is—right, this
is six—this is a total of nine, so there's six, that leaves
three here. And this is a total fifteen, there's six and that
leaves three there, okay?
Where are the tintinnabulum?
We'll worry about that. Okay, let's keep on going. Okay, so, okay,
אביי Abaye says: מנחות כנגד ארכו של ארון. Menachos keneged arkos shel
aron. כמה לוחות אוכלות בארון? שנים עשר טפחים.
Kama luchos ochlos ba-aron?
Shenaim asar tefachim.
12, right.
You're saying that 15 and a half is the inside?
Oh, we're going to get there. We're going to get there. Very
good. נשתייר שם שלשה טפחים. Nishtayer sham shlosha tefachim. So there's three
טפחים left. צא מהן טפח, חצי לכותל זה וחצי לכותל זה. Tzei
me-hen tefach, chetzi l'kosel zeh v'chetzi l'kosel zeh. What about the thickness
of the wall? Okay, with an outside measurement. So the inside measurement
is really not 15, the inside measurement is only 14. So you're
actually left only with two, okay? Now, נשתייר שם שני טפחים שבהן
ספר תורה
מונח. Nishtayer sham shnei tefachim she-ba-hen sefer torah munach.
And there was a ספר תורה sefer torah? put in the ארון,
aron, right? Now you maybe didn't know that because it says משה
Moshe at the end of דברים Devarim writes a ספר תורה sefer
torah and he gives it to the לויים Levi'im and he says:
לקוח את ספר התורה הזה ושמתם אתו בצד ארון ברית השם. Lakioach
et sefer hatorah hazeh v'samtem oto b'tzad aron berit Hashem. So it
says בצד ארון ברית השם. b'tzad aron berit Hashem. This is being
read בצד, b'tzad, next to, means on the inside at the edge,
okay?
The shelf is another opinion. This is
inside, okay? שנאמר. She-ne-emar. Now what's the proof that it was inside?
This has got to be the best גמרא Gemorah ever. The proof
that the ספר תורה Sefer Torah was inside
was: אין בארון רק שני לוחות האבנים אשר הניח שם משה. Ein
ba-aron rak shnei luchos ha-avanim asher hiniach sham Moshe. מה "אין בארון
רק"? מיעוט אחר מיעוט, ואין מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות. Ma 'ein
ba-aron rak'? Miyut achar miyut, v'ein miyut achar miyut ela l'rabot. There
is absolutely nothing there except the לוחות luchot means that there was
a
ספר תורה Sefer Torah? there.
What about the מן? mann? We
will get there. Okay, אלא לרבות ספר תורה שמונח בארון. ela l'rabot
sefer torah shemunach ba-aron. Okay, so, פרנסת ארון לארכו, צא פרנסת ארון
לארכו, צא פרנסת ארון לרחבו. parnasat aron l'arko, tzei parnasat aron l'arko,
tzei parnasat aron l'rochbo. So now you did the length, now go
do the width. כמה לוחות אוכלות בארון? ששה טפחים. Kama luchos ochlos
ba-aron? Shisha tefachim. So now your ספר תורה Sefer Torah here, okay,
well was also ששה טפחים, shisha tefachim, there you get the idea
of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah being ששה טפחים, shisha tefachim, right?
Exactly. Notice six by two. Whoa! Now we got something, six by
two. You see that? Right? There's two left here and it fits
into that width and it's got the remainder of the—and it's got
the other dimension the same as that. So that's exactly your six
by two.
So what do you do with the extra three?
Well that's air space in the back. We'll get there. It's cut
down. Right, well we'll have to discuss that air space in the
back. One minute. Okay, so one minute, wait a minute, okay hold
on. צא פרנסת ארון לרחבו, כמה לוחות אוכלות בארון? ששה. Tzei parnasat
aron l'rochbo, kama luchos ochlos ba-aron? Shisha. נשתייר שם שלשה טפחים. Nishtayer
sham shlosha tefachim. Three. צא מהן טפח, חצי לכותל זה וחצי לכותל
זה. Tzei me-hen tefach, chetzi l'kosel zeh v'chetzi l'kosel zeh.
Three becomes two because these are the inner dimensions, okay? וחצי לכותל
זה. v'kosel zeh. נשתייר שם שני טפחים שלא יהא ספר תורה נכנס
ויוצא כשהוא דחוק, דברי רבי מאיר. Nishtayer sham shnei tefachim shelo yei
sefer torah nichnas v'yotzei k'shehu dachuk, divrei Rabi Meir.
In order that you are able to, right, if everything is totally
tight, how do you take it out? So you need a little
excess. Now it's still very tight here, but okay, you move it
a little back, you get a little access, you're able to take
it out. Now the question I'm saying is: what? They opened up
the ארון aron on a regular basis to take out the ספר
תורה? Sefer Torah, Now there is actually a
famous—what is it, not מסכת סופרים, Masechet Soferim, is it a פרקי...
Pirkei... where is it? One of these—there's one that says שלשה ספרי
תורה נמצאו בהיכל, shlosha sifrei torah nimtze'u ba-heichal, you know, that actually
explains that the reason that they have some of the—some of the
words, the way they determine the proper text of our ספר תורה
Sefer Torah. according to this, I'm forgetting where it was, I don't
think it was מסכת סופרים, Masechet Soferim, it was one of those
other, anyway, מסכתות קטנות, masechtot ktanot, where it says that they found
שלשה ספרי תורה shlosha sifrei torah in the היכל, heichal, and that
there were two of them had—and in order to determine the right
text they took like a—a democratic, like a vote, essentially. Anytime there
was a con—there were differences between the texts, they did the one
that was replicated in two out of the three. What if there's
all three were different? I don't know. Anyway, and that actually explains
that the reason you have some of the words that have the
dots over them was because there's actually a question
whether... In ancient Greece, they actually would put dots over a word
to indicate that it should be deleted. So that's actually very interesting.
It all sounds heretical, but it's in the—it's in the גמרא. Gemara
So or in the תלמודית Talmudic sources. Anyway, so that actually seems
that they would access them to check the right text, okay, which
seems to be, I mean, why else are you going to access?
But really? You like open up the ארון Aron to get out
the—I mean even if you have it somewhere in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, this is where you would have it?
So he's making other ספרי תורה. Sifrei Torah.
Exactly. This is like, you know, my father used to work for
the National Bureau of Standards, and the one thing I remember I
was like five years old she showed me there was they had
like a meter, like a perfect meter that all other meters were
measured against, you know? So this was like the ספר תורה Sefer
Torah that was the text that all other ספרי תורה. Sifrei Torah.
But the question is, how often are you going into the קודש
קדשים? Kodesh Kodashim? I thought only the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So if you take a look at תוספות,
Tosafot, he says, שלא יהא ספר תורה נכנס ויוצא כשהוא דחוק. shelo
yehei Sefer Torah nichnas viyotze keshehu dachuk. ואם תאמר, ve'im tomar, והלא
לא היו מוציאין אותו מן הארון, vehalo lo hayu motzi'in oto min
ha'aron, ואסור להיכנס לבית קודש הקדשים, ve'asur lehikanes leveit Kodesh Hakodashim, ביום
הכיפורים לא עסקינן, beYom Hakipurim lo askinan, בסדר יומא שהיה מוציאו. beseder
Yoma shehaya motzi'o. Wait, why would we take it out on יום
כיפור? Yom Kippur? While you're there, כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, while you're
there anyway, why not get the ספר תורה? Sefer Torah ויש לומר,
veyesh lomar, דלצורך כדי לתקן שרי. delitzorech kedei letaken sharei. But that
does not
mean, like you were saying, to fix other ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah,
to fix it. ושרי להיכנס לבית קודש הקדשים, vesharei lehikanes leveit Kodesh
Hakodashim, כדאמרינן בעירובין, ked'amrinan be'Eruvin, והכי נמי יכולין להיכנס שם כדי לתקן
ספר תורה כדי שלא יתעפש, vehachi nami yecholin lehikanes sham kedei letaken
Sefer Torah kedei shelo yit'apesh, so it would not get moldy. ויתקלקל,
veyitkalkel, יירד דבש, yeired devash, וגם שחרשי vegam shecharashai וכו', vechu, etc.,
etc. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara
leaves that open. תוספות Tosafot explains you would take it in order
to air it out, but it is, there are other sources that
speak about ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
that served as the basic text on which everything else was based.
Yes.
You know that first in ספר מלכים, Sefer Melachim, yeah, would that
they're using to say that there's a ספר תורה Sefer Torah. in
the ארון? Aron? Yes. By that time, that ספר תורה Sefer Torah,
would have been hundreds of, many hundreds of years old. Okay. By
the end of בית ראשון, Bayis Rishon, right, it would have been
several hundred years more. Okay, you've been what?
We have scrolls from that far back? They never come or have
a defect? I don't know.
Okay, moving on. All right, so it says like this, moving on.
Okay, now. I wonder what פנסת הארון? pinasat ha'aron? Like, like לפרנס,
lefarnes, it's like you filled it
up, I think is actually what, yeah.
Yeah, exactly. Exactly, like if it's אוכל בארון, ochel ba'aron, it's eating
the space, you fill it up, you're מפרנס.
mefarnes. Okay. It's like languages, yeah.
Okay, so it says like this. Okay, שלא יהא ספר תורה נכנס
ויוצא כשהוא דחוק, shelo yehei Sefer Torah nichnas viyotze keshehu dachuk, דברי
רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה אומר. Rabbi Yehuda omer. Now
we didn't say what you did, so that's apparently that was open
space. All right, let's hold off. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
באמה בת חמישה טפחים. be'amah bat chamisha tefachim. Now רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says when you would measure an אמה amah in the כלים
keilim of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it would be a five
טפח tefach אמה, amah, not a six טפח tefach אמה. amah. It's
a general position about all the כלים keilim in the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so והלוחות. vehaluchot. Now, so therefore, we gotta change
all these numbers. So, so let's do it out. So two and
a half, okay, so two and a half times five is twelve
and a half. One and a half times five is seven and
a half. Okay, fine. Now let's figure this out. What, and also
we gotta do the height either? No, the height is not relevant
for us now. Okay, so רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, והלוחות
אורכן שישה ורוחבן שישה. vehaluchot orkan shisha verochban shisha. We're not debating
the six by six, okay, because apparently that was the מסורה. masorah.
All right? So if it's six by six, so there ain't gonna
be no ספר תורה, Sefer Torah.
I'll tell you that,
because it's twelve and a half, so you're only left here with
twelve. Okay? And if it's seven and a half, so you only
left here with one, and this is by the way, these are
the outside measurements, okay? You only left here with one and a
half. And now we have to deal with anyway the thickness of
the walls. Oh, right, I understand. Okay. והלוחות אורכן שישה ורוחבן שישה
ועוביין שלושה, vehaluchot orkan shisha verochban shisha ve'ovyan shlosha, מונחות באורכו של
ארון. munachot be'orko shel aron. כמה לוחות אוכלות בארון? kama luchot ochlot
ba'aron? שנים עשר טפחים. shneim asar tefachim. נשאר שם חצי טפח. nish'ar
sham chatzi tefach. Okay. Yeah, well one, it's a half. נשאר שם
חצי טפח. nish'ar sham chatzi tefach. אצבע לכותל זה ואצבע לכותל זה.
etzba lakotel zeh ve'etzba lakotel zeh. So a טפח, tefach, assuming it's
four טפחים—sorry, four finger-breadths—so one finger here and one finger here means
a quarter טפח tefach here, a quarter טפח tefach here. So it
was a totally tight fit, okay? Totally tight. Okay, now. אצבע לכותל
זה. etzba lakotel zeh. פנסת הארון אורכו. pinasat ha'aron orko. That's the
length. צא מהם פנסת הארון לרוחבו. tze meihem pinasat ha'aron lerochbo. כמה
לוחות אוכלות בארון? kama luchot ochlot ba'aron? שישה טפחים. shisha tefachim. נשתייר
שם טפח ומחצה. nishtayer sham tefach umetchah. צא מהם חצי טפח. tze
meihem chatzi tefach. אצבע ומחצה לכותל זה ואצבע ומחצה לכותל זה. etzba
umetchah lakotel zeh ve'etzba umetchah lakotel zeh. It's a funny גרסא girsa
because if so, a finger and a half, that's three fingers, that's
half of a טפח, tefach, that's three quarters of a טפח. tefach.
There's different questions of exactly the גרסא. girsa. But anyway, you take
out a little bit for the width of the walls and you're
left with... נשאר שם Sham טפח tefach *nish'ar sham tefach*. Right, so
really it should be one finger for each, the same way this
was one finger for each, and you have one טפח *tefach* of
open space. Okay, so נשאר שם Shem, טפח *nish'ar sham tefach*, שבו
עומדים עמודים Amudim? *shebo omdim amudim*. Now, here’s something you didn’t know
was in the ארון Aron, *aron*. Okay, there was these like poles,
the same way there were like poles for a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah *sefer Torah*. Obviously you don’t need it for לוחות luchot *luchot*,
but they’re symbolic. Okay, what were they symbolic? Like pillars. שנאמר *shenemar*:
אפריון עשה לו המלך שלמה מעצי הלבנון *apiryon asa lo hamelech Shlomo
me'atzei Halevanon*. Right, it's a, you know, a... now an אפריון *apiryon*
is like a, is like a bed, right? Like a whatever, a
palanquin, right? As the... שלמה *Shlomo* made for him from the, from
the cedars of the Lebanon. Okay, cedars of Lebanon we know by
the way that the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash* was made
by the cedars of the Lebanon, right, and שלמה *Shlomo* made it.
עמודיו עשה כסף *amudav asa kesef*, the pillars were made out of
silver. רפידתו זהב מרכבו ארגמן *refidato zahav merkavo argaman*. Okay, so these
were poles of presumably what you would do is you would move
the, the לוחות luchot, *luchot* to the middle and they're actually would
be, the way I understand this, okay, a חצי טפח *chatzi tefach*
right here space and a חצי טפח *chatzi tefach* space, and you
would have in that space you would have a pillar of silver.
Exactly. Steinzaltz says. Excellent. Oh, brilliant. Okay, so I bet, I bet
mine is more artistic than this. Okay, so. Okay. Okay. So, okay.
And this was in the ארון Aron *aron*. This אפריון *apiryon*? This
is in the ארון Aron *aron*. Okay, all right, so, okay, so
and if you want to look at תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, שבהן עמודים
Amudim, עומדים *shebehen amudim omdim*, תוספות *Tosafot* says, נראה לרבינו תם דסימן
להעמדת ישראל היה *nireh le'Rabeinu Tam desiman le'ha'amadat Yisrael haya*. Like it's
sort of, this was like, you know, the pillar of the Jewish
people, so the idea of a pillar, right? The תורה Torah, *Torah*
is our pillar. Okay. ולא עשאום של זהב שלא להזכיר מעשה עגל
*velo asa'um shel zahav shelo lehazkir ma'aseh egel* and then it gets
on why it's silver. Okay. So, but it also then becomes very
much obviously what's happening is according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi
Meir* you have the ספר *sefer*, physical ספר תורה Sefer Torah? *sefer
Torah* in here.
According to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* even
if not physical
ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer
Torah*, but this looks like a ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer Torah*.
You got two poles and you got the תורה Torah, *Torah* in
the middle. They're not attached. They're just there symbolically. I understand, but
it's symbolically the ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer Torah*.
You're making the
connection between the one, you know, singular לוחות Luchot. *luchot* in the
קודש קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim* that nobody has access to. Right, I want
to make a point here about the difference between, which I've made
other times, between sort of מקדש *Mikdash*-centered קדושה *kedusha* and תורה *Torah*-centered
קדושה *kedusha*. מקדש *Mikdash*-centered קדושה *kedusha* is the most inaccessible and hierarchical,
right? Only the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur,
*Yom Kippur*, in general it's כהן *Kohen*, לוי *Levi*, ישראל *Yisrael*, men
and women, טמא *tamei* and טהור *tahor*, right, it's the hardest sort
of thing to get to, right? Okay, and that's the קודש קדשים
*Kodesh Kodashim* whatever. Whereas the ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer Torah* is
לכל מונח *lechol munach*, is completely accessible for everybody. And the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, right, you know what does it say? יקרה היא
מפנינים *yekara hi mipninim*. The תורה *Torah* is greater than פנינים *pninim*.
יקרה היא מכהן גדול שנכנס לפני ולפנים *yekara hi mikohen gadol shenichnas
lifnai velifnim*. So the access, the only the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*
on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* has only access, eh, but תורה *Torah*,
it's higher than all of that. Right? So it's sort of the
universal over the most protected. And here what we're doing is we're
sort of connecting the dots. The, you know, the לוחות Luchot *luchot*,
which are straight from הקדוש ברוך הוא *Hakadosh Baruch Hu*, are being
equated with and put side-by-side the ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer Torah*,
which everybody has access to. Okay? So either it's a physical ספר
תורה Sefer Torah. *sefer Torah* according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi
Meir*, or this becomes a symbolic ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer Torah*
which is the לוחות Luchot *luchot* sitting between these two עמודים Amudim.
*amudim*. Yes. And that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* which itself was saying that
there was in addition to the לוחות Luchot *luchot* inside the ארון
Aron. *aron*, right? You quoted it earlier. Yes. So the חכמים *Chachamim*,
it's very subversive of מקדש *Mikdash*. You already have the seeds of...
Right, that's what I'm saying. You're taking within the מקדש *Mikdash* and
you're basically sort of saying, yeah, really basically is leading to having
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah *sefer Torah*. So we're having this פסוק
Pasuk *pasuk* of אפריון *apiryon*, but we're saying that the only thing
that was actually in there was not the backing or not the...
because it talks about the מרכבה *merkava*, the רפידתו *refidato*. Yeah, no,
just these poles. Yes. I don't know why. Okay, so because... I
do know why, because this makes it a symbolic ספר תורה Sefer
Torah *sefer Torah*. Yes. Is that a rabbinic intention? That's my read.
Okay.
I don't know. We all are reading the same גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
That's my interpretation. That's what's implied at here. Yes. והארגז *v'ha'argaz* ששיגרו
בו פלשתים Plishtim, דורון לאלהי ישראל *sheshigru vo Pelishtim doron l'Elohei Yisrael*.
Now, people remember the whole story where the ארון Aron *aron* was
captured in war and then they started having all
of this sickness or whatever and then the פלשתים *Pelishtim* sent it
back and they sent it back with a box filled with all
of these gold vessels.
מונח מצידו *munach mitzido*, it's put on the side of the ארון
Aron, *aron*, not inside, on the outside. שנאמר *shenemar*: ואת כלי הזהב
אשר
השבתם לו אשם תשימו בארגז מצידו *ve'et klei hazahav asher hasheivotem lo
asham tasimu va'argaz mitzido*. When you send back the ארון Aron. *aron*,
put all of these gold vessels
in a box and put it next to it.
ושלחתם אותו והלך והלך *veshilachtem oto vehalach vehalach*. And so therefore they
understand it would
always be מצידו *mitzido*.
So there in the קודש קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim* was this box, okay,
that I don’t know if it was still filled with the gold
vessels, but that’s a very strange concept. All right. Right, I don't
know what this box is doing. ועליו ספר תורה Sefer Torah. מונח,
but conveniently, once it's there, now even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, has
a ספר תורה. And by the way, a ספר תורה on a
box is evocative of the what we call the ארון, Aron which
we keep our ספר תורה in. So in the ארון Aron, itself
you have a symbolic ספר תורה. And then right outside the ארון
Aron. you have a wood box with a physical ספר תורה, which
is exactly what everybody has in their... what? It's on top of
it, right, like not in it but on top of it. Okay,
but basically, which therefore is what everybody has in their בית כנסת.
Beit Knesset. Right? So you're having almost the translation. This is like
this, becomes translated into this other box with this other תורה, right,
which is then which is then a representative of what everybody else
has. One minute. Okay, ושלחתו ועליו ספר תורה מונח שנאמר לקוח את
ספר התורה הזה ושמתם אתו מצד ארון ברית ה'. veshalachto ve'alav Sefer
Torah munach shene'emar lachoach et Sefer HaTorah hazeh vesamtem oto mitzad Aron
Brit Hashem. מצד mitzad הוא מונח ולא בתוכו. hu munach velo betocho.
ומה אני מקיים? vema ani mekayem? Okay, that's great, but what do
I do with the פסוק Pasuk אין בארון רק ein ba'aron rak
which obviously is clear that there's something else there? Now of course
I don't know why we don't just say it's the poles, but
it's got to be something more than that. לרבות שברי לוחות שמונחין
בארון. lerabot shivrei luchot shemunachin ba'aron. Ah, not just לוחות luchot, even
the שברי לוחות. shivrei luchot. רש"י Rashi said it was underneath because
remember we had height left, but you don't want to put the
שברי לוחות shivrei luchot on top, so the שברי לוחות shivrei luchot
were underneath and the לוחות luchot were on top of them שמונחין
בארון. shemunachin ba'aron. ואי סלקא דעתך ve'ee salka datach now, okay, now
we're going to now... It's just a מדרש midrash that the שברי
לוחות shivrei luchot are מונחים בארון. munachim ba'aron. Yes, it's not in
the פסוקים. pesukim. Yeah. Right. No, there are other places. Yeah, לוחות
ושברי לוחות מונחים בארון luchot veshivrei luchot munachim ba'aron is a common
theme. Okay. Is it for both אמר רבי יהודה amar Rabbi Yehuda
or just... No, well, presume... we're going to get to that. We're
going to make a... we're going to figure out how רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir learns that. Now, here's back... that was the whole reason
we discussed this was to get to the dimensions of the ספר
תורה. So based on רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, we had it was
exactly six by two, which should be perfect. It should be exactly
what we've been saying. So
the גמרא Gemara says ואי סלקא דעתך ve'ee salka datach ספר תורה
דהיקפו ו' מכדי. Sefer Torah dehekefo vav michdi. So if you're going
to say that its circumference was six and its length was six,
כל שיש בהיקפו ג' טפחים יש בו רוחב טפח. kol sheyesh behekefo
gimel tefachim yesh bo rochav tefach. Anything that has a circumference of
six has a width, a diameter of what? Again, that basically means
pi is three. Okay. וכיון דאמצעיתו נגלה. vekevan de'emtzoito nigleh. Now, all
of this was to prove that a ספר תורה must have only
one pole and not two poles. Because if you had two poles,
okay, then the pole is going to take up some extra width.
It's not just going to be six. If the whole thing is
six, right, is it whatever and then you need the other pole,
it's going to... I mean, it's going to take up more... it's
going to be more than your two טפחים width. If the circumference
is six, then the טפח then the two טפחים width plus the
pole is going to be bigger. So וכיון דאמצעיתו נגלה נפיק ליה
מטפי מתרי טפחי רווחא דביני ביני. vekevan de'emtzoito nigleh nafik lei midei
mitrei tefachei revacha debeini beini. The space between the two, right? Because
if here you've got your thing that is six around and two
wide, but if it's got another pole, then this... then even if
it's just at the beginning, you know, whatever here is at the
other pole, this little bit extra is going to increase the width
of two. You're going to be wider than two. Okay? Your circumference
is six, your length is six, but you only have a space
of two, okay, which would be perfect for if all you had
was the one column. But if you have to have another... meaning,
now of course why didn't you... you could always put it on
top?
You mean it's the thing of the קלף, not the poles. In
other words, you wrap the קלף then you stick in the poles
afterwards. That's what...
I don't understand, where's the other pole going? If the whole circumference
is six...
It's at a triangle there that you could have in the little
bottom corner as you've drawn it, right?
What? If here was the לוחות, luchot if this is a side
view, six, six, two. Right, but you see that there... oh, you
mean why didn't it stuck in right there at the gap? That's
how... that's a good question. Why couldn't sort of figure it that's
in that gap that's created between that space? It is attached. So
why can't you just fit it
in? No, no, but if it's like this, I mean, I'm not
a good enough artist to draw it.
If it had a... a end of the עצי חיים, atzei chayim,
it had actually some width, right?
I don't know, you'll have to figure it out. But you're right,
it's a good point. You do like... there is a gap here.
Also, why didn't you put it up there? Okay, which is what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say eventually anyway. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this: נפיק ליה רווחא דביני ביני. nafik lei
revacha debeini beini. בתרי פוסטא היכי יתיב? betrei pusta heichi yativ?
How can it sit in two טפחים? So the גמרא says
אמר רב אחא בר יעקב ספר עזרה, amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov
Sefer Azara, Sefer in the
עזרה, Azara, עזרה... Azara... interesting he says עזרה Azara because this is
the קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, but... but that phrase of ספר עזרה
Sefer Azara echoes that other... that
Talmudic line I told you about, שלשה ספרים נמצאו בעזרה. shlosha sefarim
nimtzeu ba'azara. Okay, ספר עזרה לתחילתו הוא נגלל. Sefer Azara litchilato hu
niglal. Fine, the one in the בית המקדש only had one pole.
Okay, it didn't have two poles. It only fine. All right. Which
is the... לתחילתו הוא נגלל?
litchilato hu niglal? לתחילתו הוא נגלל, litchilato hu niglal, that's
what תוספות says before his point, it starts from the end and
you roll towards the beginning. You don't roll from both ends. towards
the middle, you roll it all up into one. And there's only
one pole?
There's only one pole.
Like the אמצע Emtza means there are two poles so you can
be in any place in the middle and לתחילתו Letchilato means there's
only one pole so you roll it towards the beginning. Okay? So
the גמרא says דחקי תרי בתרי היכי יתיבי. Dachaki Trei Betrei Heichi
Yasivi. Still, you can't, you know, you need a little space to
move things in and out. How do you get two, something that's
exactly two טפחים wide in the space that's exactly two טפחים? Right,
you need a little wiggle room. So אמר רב אשי Amar Rav
Ashi דכריך בי פורתא וכרכיה לעיל. Decharich Bei Purta Vecharchayei Le'eil. All
right, so you leave over a little bit and you leave, so
again, why do we need to say this with the pole, I
don't know, but you leave, you don't make it, you make this
1.9 to give you a little wiggle space and the extra little
bit, you know, you wrap here, you know, you know, you have
a little bit wrapped on the top, okay? Is that sort of
clear what we're talking about? Imagine you got a מגילה and you
like wrap a little bit of it, right? You have the basic
big scroll there and like a little bit wrapped on top to
give you a little room. What? This diagram? Yeah, okay, that's a
better diagram than I was drawing. Okay. So the גמרא says like
this. אוקיי. Okay. רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, now רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
מקמי דאייתו ארגז Mikamei Delayeitu Argaz before they brought the ארגז Argaz
from the פלשתים, ספר תורה היכי הוה יתיב, Sefer Torah Heichi Hava
Yasiv, where were they put a ספר תורה? Because the ספר תורה
had to be near the ארון. Aron, דפא הוה נפיק מיניה, Dappa
Hava Nafik Minei, fine, there was a little shelf that came out
from the back of the ארון Aron that they would put the
ספר תורה on. יתיב עליה ספר תורה. Yasiv Alayei Sefer Torah. All
right. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir האי מצד ארון מאי עביד ליה? Hai
Mitzad Aron Mai Avid Lei? It says put the ספר תורה next
to the ארון, Aron. not in the ארון. Aron. הוא מיבעי ליה
דמנח ליה מצד ולא מנח ליה ביני לוחות. Hu Miba'ei Lei Demanach
Lei Mitzad Velo Manach Lei Beini Luchot. Yes, it would be in
the ארון Aron at one of the sides, at one of the
inner sides, not between the לוחות. luchot. Okay? It wouldn't be in
the middle of the ארון, Aron? it would be at the side,
but in the inside of it. Okay? ולעולם בגוויה דארונא יתיב, Ule'olam
Begavei De'arona Yasiv, it would be in the inner part of the
ארון. Aron. This is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir but towards the edge,
towards the wall, not in the middle. So you mean like where
those bars were? Yeah, well, actually here, because for him it would
be here, but it wouldn't be between them. It would be in
the side of the ארון, Aron. inside the ארון Aron? but at
the side, not at the middle. But I thought the first space
is taken up. No, no, no, we're not answering that anymore. We're
answering that the פסוק Pasuk says put it by the side of
the ארון. Aron. And according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, it would
be on the outside. No, I'm on the inside. So what does
it mean? Right, the פסוק Pasuk says take the ספר תורה and
put it מצד ארון ברית השם. Mitzad Aron Berit Hashem. So how
does that work for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, who says it's on
the inside? So he says it's on the inside but at a
wall, against a wall, not in the middle. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
עמודים היכי הוו קיימי? Amudim Heichi Havu Kaymi? So רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir what would you do with these עמודים? Of course you need
these עמודים, because as we learned from the פסוק in שיר השירים.
Shir HaShirim. So the גמרא says מבראי. Mibara'ei. Fine, those would be
on the outside of the ארון. Aron. So everybody would have, you
know, a ספר תורה and everybody would have the עמודים. It's just
a debate which was on the inside of the ארון Aron, and
which was on the outside. רבי מאיר, שברי לוחות דמונחים בארון מנא
ליה? Shivrei Luchot Demonachim Ba'aron Mena Lei? And where do you know
the שברי לוחות Shivrei Luchot were מונחים Munachim in the ארון? Aron
Because you can't be from the פסוק אין בארון רק, Ein Ba'aron
Rak, because that you learned that you have to have a ספר
תורה. So נפקא ליה מדרב הונא. Nafka Lei Midrav Huna. From רב
הונא, Rav Huna, דאמר רב הונא, De'amar Rav Huna, מאי דכתיב, Mai
Dechtiv, what's meant by the verse, אשר נקרא שם שם השם צבאות
יושב הכרובים? Asher Nikra Sham Shem Hashem Tzeva'ot Yoshev Hakruvim? That it
is called there the name of השם צבאות. Hashem Tzeva'ot. So it's
שם Sham is שם, Shem? but it's treating like שם שם Sham
Sham or שם שם. Shem Shem. There are two things there, or
two, you know, two things with God's name there, if you want
to read it שם שם Sham Sham or שם שם. Shem Shem.
עליו, Alav, מלמד שלוחות ושברי לוחות מונחים בארון. Melamed Sheluchot Veshivrei Luchot
Munachim Ba'aron. That there's both the לוחות luchot. and the שברי לוחות
Shivrei Luchot מונחים Munachim in the ארון. aron. ואידך, Ve'idach, the other
approach, what does he do with the doubling of the word שם
or שם? ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדרבי יוחנן, Hahu Miba'ei Lei Lechedrabbi Yochanan,
דאמר רבי יוחנן אמר רבי שמעון בן יוחי, De'amar Rabbi Yochanan Amar
Rabbi Shimon Ben Yochai, מלמד שהשם וכל כינויו מונחים בארון. Melamed Shehashem
Vechol Kinuyav Munachim Ba'aron. God's name and all the variations of God's
name were in the ארון. Now what does that mean that they
were in the ארון? Because again, this is רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda
and רבי יהודה said that the ספר תורה was on the outside
of the ארון. So is he saying that the לוחות luchot had
somehow hidden within them all of the different variations? It's one thing
to say the ספר תורה has all the variations of God's names,
okay? So it's not exactly clear. Like a list of all the...
Oh, you mean like they just had what, some separate list that
they kept there? That's interesting. I don't know. Does it say there,
David, does it say what that means? All of the things of
God's name were in the ארון. I thought it just meant that
that was some like mystically that they were hidden. Oh, they mean
it literally, there was like some list that they put there. That's
interesting. אוקיי. Okay.
ואידך נמי מיבעי ליה להכי.
Ve'idach Nami
Miba'ei Lei Le'hachi. Ah, don't you need it to tell you that?
אין הכי נמי. Ein Hechi Nami. Yes, you're right. רבי מאיר says
you're right. אלא שברי לוחות דמונחים בארון מנא ליה? Ela Shivrei Luchot
Demonachim Ba'aron Mena Lei? So then where do you learn if שם
שם Sham Sham tells you all of God's names were there? There
were so many things in the ארון, it was so busy. Right?
When you think about the, you know, יום כיפור, he goes in,
it's like the ultimate of simplicity. All of a sudden, there's like
the ארון is packed full with stuff. There's all this stuff on
the outside. It's like a backpack for a trip and you're like
going to it and you're like, oh wait, that's... Right, right. So
anyway, it's a good point. So it says like this, so therefore,
שברי לוחות דמונחים בארון מנא ליה? Shivrei Luchot Demonachim Ba'aron Mena Lei?
נפקא ליה מדתני דבי רבי ישמעאל. Nafka Lei Midtani Debei Rabbi Yishmael.
תני דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tani Debei Rabbi Yishmael, אשר שברת, Asher Shibarta,
those לוחות luchot that you broke, ושמתם בארון, Vesamtam Ba'aron, ושמתם, Vesamtam,
מלמד שהלוחות... Melamed Sheluchot... ושברי לוחות מונחים בארון. v'shivrei luchot munachim ba'aron.
אשר שברת ושמתם, Asher shibarta v'sam-tam, right, even the ones you broke,
put them in the ארון. ואידך V'idach ההוא מבעי ליה hahu mibaya
lei לריש לקיש, le-Reish Lakish, דאמר ריש לקיש d'amar Reish Lakish אשר
שברת, asher shibarta, אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה, amar lo HaKadosh
Baruch Hu le-Moshe,
יישר כחך ששברת, yashar kochacha she-shibarta, right, that was
the right thing to do to break the לוחות, that was what
was necessary at that time, but I don't know, but I do
want to say again interestingly, if you accept
my read here that what
חז״ל Chazal are doing is they're translating like the לוחות which were
to be totally inaccessible to the ספר תורה which is totally and
making this equation, the יישר כחך ששברת yashar kochacha she-shibarta is also
sort of saying something about, you know, the lack of the need
for the לוחות themselves. Right? There's a power even broken, like there's
a power in the broken לוחות. We didn't, ultimately don't need the
physical לוחות. We have the תורה, right? So I don't know, maybe
that's putting it a little bit of an extreme. Obviously you'd rather
say no, no at that for that moment that was the right
thing and there was other לוחות that were gonna come now to
make them up, but I think ending this whole discussion with it's
a good thing we have broken, we had the breaking of the
לוחות is a certain power in terms of then talking about the
accessibility of like the ספר תורה. Yes. What was the מטה אהרן?
Matteh Aharon? Yeah, so we didn't deal with the rest of the
stuff. I managed to push you off without giving you an answer.
Okay.